"Benefits of Quinoa for Lowering Triglycerides"
Approximately 90% of the
world's calories are provided
by less than 1% of the quarter
million known edible plants.
The big three are wheat, corn,
and rice, the reliance upon which
may be unsustainable given
the ongoing climate crisis.
This has spurned new interest into
underutilized crops like quinoa,
which might do better
with the drought and heat.
Quinoa has only been introduced in
the Northern hemisphere recently,
but humans have been eating
quinoa for more than 7,000 years.
Is there any truth to the
superfood designation
or is it all just marketing hooey?
Quinoa is a pseudo-grain,
since the plant it comes
from isn't a type of grass.
Technically it's a seed-like fruit.
It does have a lot of protein,
and also lots of vitamins and minerals,
but so do all whole grains.
Yeah, it has more protein
than other grains,
but since when do we
need more protein?
Fiber is what we're sorely lacking,
and its fiber content is relatively
modest compared to barley or rye.
Pretty strong on folate and vitamin E,
and leads the pack on
magnesium, iron and zinc.
So nutritious?
Sure, but when I think superfood,
I think some sort of
special clinical benefit.
So broccoli is a superfood, strawberries
are a superfood, garlic is a superfood.
But what about quinoa?
Consumer demand is up, thanks in
part to perceived health benefits.
In lab animals it has all
sorts of purported benefits,
but there have been
very few human studies.
The first trial was a before and after
study of quinoa granola bars
that showed drops in triglycerides and
cholesterol, but with no control group
you don't know how much of that would
have happened without the quinoa.
This is the kind of study I wanted to
see: a randomized controlled trial.
And about a cup a day of
cooked quinoa for 12 weeks
led to a 36% drop in triglycerides.
That's comparable to what one gets
with triglyceride-lowering drugs
or high dose fish oil supplements.
Which is better, regular
quinoa or red quinoa?
Well, red does have about
twice the antioxidant power,
leading the investigators to conclude
that red quinoa might significantly
contribute to the management and/or
prevention of degenerative diseases
associated with free radical damage,
though it's never been put to the test.
What about black quinoa?
Both red and black appear
equally antioxidant rich,
both beating out the more
conventional white.
The only caveat I could find
is to inform your doctor
before your next colonoscopy, else
they might mistake it for parasites.
A colonoscopy revealed numerous
egg-like tan-yellow ovoid objects
of unclear cause, but it
was just undigested quinoa.